{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This poem’s main subjects are described as \"deaf even to the hoots of tired, outstripped Five- Nines that dropped behind.\" This poem describes a man drowning \"under a green sea,\" and it describes the title phrase as \"the old Lie.\" It opens by depicting a group \"bent double, like old beggars under sacks,\" and was written shortly after the completion of \"Anthem for Doomed Youth.\" For 10 points, name this Wilfred Owen poem that describes a World War I gas attack.",
      "answer": "\"Dulce et Decorum Est\" <KG> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, the publishers of Woodhull & Claflin's Weekly were arrested for reporting on an adulterous affair. The author of Society as I Have Found It, Ward Mcallister, ran this city's social scene and claimed that only 400 of its residents mattered. The original Lord and Taylor was founded along this city's Ladies' Mile. For 10 points, name this birthplace and frequent literary target of socialite Edith Wharton, whose Gilded Age aristocracy were known as \"Knickerbockers.\"",
      "answer": "New York City, New York <JB>"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer supposedly wrote the aria “Hear Ye, Israel” with Jenny Lind in mind. His fifth symphony was written for the 300th anniversary of the Augsburg Confession and quotes “A Mighty Fortress Is Our God” in its finale. This composer of the Reformation Symphony revived interest in J.S. Bach with his performance of the St. Matthew Passion. For 10 points, name this Jewish-born composer of the oratorio Elijah who also wrote some Songs Without Words.",
      "answer": "Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy <CW> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler conquered Llywelyn the Last, annexing Wales in the Statute of Rhuddlan. This person won the Battle of Evesham against Simon de Montfort in the Second Barons’ War and joined Louis the Saint on a failed crusade. This son of Henry III won the Battle of Falkirk Muir against William Wallace, whom he later had executed, and he was called the “Hammer of the Scots.” For 10 points, name this English monarch known for his long legs.",
      "answer": "Edward I <JZ> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "In response to European tariffs on this product, Lyndon B. Johnson imposed a tariff on light trucks, including Volkswagen vans. Federal regulations on this product were struck down in Schechter v. United States, which also invalidated the National Industrial Recovery Act. A business that specializes in this product was founded by Harland Sanders in 1930 while Frank Perdue was a 20th century mogul in this agribusiness field. For 10 points, name this chief product of KFC.",
      "answer": "chickens <KG> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
    },
    {
      "question": "Before his sentencing by the Governor's Council, John Punch was one of these people. Sponsorship of these people was rewarded with land via the headright system. Redemptioners often became these people, who were paid \"freedom dues.\" The use of these people lost popularity after they participated in Bacon's Rebellion. For 10 points, name these people who did unpaid work for several years in exchange for transportation to America.",
      "answer": "indentured servants <JB>"
    },
    {
      "question": "A presidential nominee of this party was later given a chastity belt by nemesis Gloria Allred. This third party claimed there was \"not a dime's worth of difference\" between the Republicans and Democrats. One of its vice presidential nominees was an Air Force General who once threatened to bomb enemies \"back to the Stone Age.\" For 10 points, name this conservative party that nominated Curtis LeMay as the running mate of Alabama's George Wallace in 1968.",
      "answer": "American Independent Party <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to this battle, one commander gave command of half his army to Joseph Tarchaniotes, whose fate is unclear. The losing side’s leader was betrayed by Andronicus Doukas, and was blinded by members of the Doukas family upon his return. Byzantine historians considered this battle a major turning point as the Empire later lost control over Anatolia. For 10 points, which 1071 battle did Emperor Romanos IV lose to Alp Arslan in a major victory for the Seljuk Turks?",
      "answer": "Battle of Manzikert <TR> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "A person with this occupation adopted the pseudonym \"John Palmer.\" The most famous person of this occupation was assisted by Matthew King and was the subject of a biography by Richard Bayes. These people often ordered passersby to \"stand and deliver.\" A person with this occupation falls in love with the landlord's daughter Bess in an Alfred Noyes poem. For 10 points, name this occupation held by Dick Turpin, who robbed travelers while on horseback.",
      "answer": "highwaymen <KG> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "A restored scene in this film featured a historical character talking about \"eating oysters\" and \"eating snails.\" The title character's life in this film is spared by an African named Draba. Screenwriter Dalton Trumbo's credit for this film helped to break the blacklist era. In the climax of this film, numerous people claim to be the title character and are crucified by Crassus' men. For 10 points, name this Stanley Kubrick film starring Kirk Douglas as a rebellious gladiator.",
      "answer": "Spartacus <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Domingo Liotta and Denton Cooley were the first to use one of these devices on a human. The AbioCor is a popular model of this device, an early recipient of which was a dentist named Barney Clark. Willem Kolf and Arthur Jarvik designed another one of these devices, which allowed its user to survive for 112 days after suffering congestive failure. For 10 points, name these mechanical device designed to completely replace a particular organ after an infarction.",
      "answer": "Artificial heart <EM> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country is where Rudolf Roessler operated the anti-Nazi Lucy Spy Ring. During World War II, this country's National Redoubt strategy was announced in a speech given on the symbolic Rutli field by its leader Henri Guisan. This country was the target of the cancelled Operation Tannenbaum. This country's National Bank controversially bought plundered gold from the Nazis. For 10 points, name this Alpine country which maintained its traditional neutrality during World War II.",
      "answer": "Switzerland <JB> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This legislative body enacted a Dependency Pension Plan guaranteeing lifetime retirement benefits for veterans of its country's civil war. The first Speakership of so-called \"Czar\" Thomas Reed, and the first Senate presidency of Levi P. Morton, happened in this set of legislative sessions. The Sherman Silver Purchase and Anti-Trust Acts were passed by, for 10 points, what 1888-1890 session of Congress that irked Benjamin Harrison with its unprecedented spending?",
        "answer": "Billion-Dollar Congress"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What session of Congress passed the Naturalization Act and argued about whether to assume state debts while meeting in Federal Hall, Philadelphia?",
        "answer": "First United States Congress <MJ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Hadfield attempted to assassinate this king at Drury Lane. The Third Earl of Bute strongly advised this ruler not to marry Sarah Lennox. Despite this king's enmity against Charles Fox, he placed Fox in Grenville's \"Ministry of All the Talents.\" This ruler set up a regency near the end of his life due to his insanity, which may have been caused by porphyria. For 10 points, name this British king who reigned during the American Revolution.",
        "answer": "George III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What man, the founder of The North Briton news magazine, was charged with libel for his unrestrained criticism of George III?",
        "answer": "John Wilkes <JL> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2014, this man dissolved his country’s Charities and Not-For-Profits Commission as part of Repeal Day. He refused to allow the abortion drug RU486 while health minister in 2006. This man has pushed to “stop the boats” of asylum seekers with Operation Sovereign Borders. He introduced legislation to repeal his country’s carbon tax on the first day he took power from Labor PM Kevin Rudd. For 10 points, name this current Prime Minister of Australia.",
        "answer": "Anthony John \"Tony\" Abbott"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tony Abbott is one of twelve leaders currently negotiating what free trade deal which also includes the United States and various Asian countries?",
        "answer": "Trans-Pacific Partnership <CW> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Otto III denied the validity of the Diploma Ottonianum and this other document. This document incorrectly used the terms \"satraps\" and \"consuls\" when describing a gift that, according to legend, was given to Sylvester I for curing a leper. Lorenzo Valla proved that, for 10 points, what document purporting to give spiritual and temporal power to the Pope could not have been issued by the first Christian Roman Emperor?",
        "answer": "Donation of Constantine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Donation of Constantine was often informally invoked during what controversy over the power to appoint bishops?",
        "answer": "Investiture Controversy <DW> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In his Letter Concerning Toleration, Locke said that Catholics and this group of people were threats to government. David Silverman heads an organization advocating for these people, which was originally founded by “the most hated woman in America”, Madelyn Murray O’Hair. A prominent advocate of this position argues that its adherents should be called “brights” and outlined several arguments for it in The God Delusion. For 10 points, name this type of person who does not believe in a god.",
        "answer": "Atheists"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which atheist, philosopher, and mathematician wrote the essay “Why I am Not a Christian” and urged for nuclear disarmament for the US and USSR?",
        "answer": "Bertrand Russell <EM> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Winston Churchill called this man the “organizer of victory.” This person created the individual replacement system implemented by Leslie McNair. He unsuccessfully tried to broker peace in the Chinese Civil War. One program this man created was announced at a commencement address at Harvard, after his tenure as Chief of Staff of the Army during World War II. For 10 points, name this Secretary of State whose namesake plan provided aid to Europe after World War II.",
        "answer": "George Marshall"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Contemporaneously, Harry Truman issued a namesake \"doctrine\" implemented to prevent what two countries from falling to Communism?",
        "answer": "Turkey and Greece <JZ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's use of rough concrete in Marseille’s Unite d’habitation inspired the Brutalist movement. This architect proposed erecting a series of cross-shaped towers in place of central Paris in the Plan Voisin. His “scheme 23” was combined with Oscar Niemeyer’s proposal for the final design of the UN headquarters. He was inspired by ship design to create an International Style villa which epitomized his “five points.” For 10 points, name this Franco-Swiss architect of the Villa Savoye.",
        "answer": "Le Corbusier"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After it lost Lahore to Pakistan, Le Corbusier designed the Open Hand Monument for what new capital of India’s Punjab province?",
        "answer": "Chandigarh, India <CW> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This town was the site of a feud between the Putnam and Porter families. Conflict in this town intensified with the arrival of the Reverend Samuel Parris. This town established the Court of Oyer and Terminer. The odd behavior of Betty Parris and Abigail Williams led to a period of hysteria in this town that claimed the lives of Giles Corey and others. For 10 points, name this Massachusetts town that put people, mostly young girls, on trial in 1692 for alleged paranormal activity.",
        "answer": "Salem"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the women that Betty Parris and Abigail Williams identified as their tormentors was what West Indian slave in their household?",
        "answer": "Tituba <SH> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Journalist Bjorn Kumm wrote an eyewitness account of this event, which took place near Vallegrande, for The New Republic. The corpse of this event's victim was tied to the landing shafts of a helicopter and then flown away from U.S.-trained Rangers who watched it occur. The victim of this event allegedly said \"I know you have come to kill me. Shoot, coward. You are only going to kill a man,\" seven years after he had been immortalized in a photo by Alberto Korda while wearing a star-studded beret. It took place in Bolivia in 1967. For 10 points, name this violent end for a Marxist former confidant of Fidel Castro.",
        "answer": "assassination of Ernesto \"Che\" Guevara <MJ> {II}"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Like Che Guevara, which American outlaw born with the name Robert Parker, was shot in Bolivia?",
        "answer": "Butch Cassidy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The contrast agent Thorotrast was withdrawn due to it causing angiosarcoma of this organ. Baruch Blumberg won a Nobel Prize for a vaccine against a virus that infects this organ. Vesalius proved that this organ was not the source of veins. Karl Wilhelm von Kupffer twice misidentified the function of cells in this organ that are now named after him. This organ was thought to be the source of the appetitive soul and the four humors. For 10 points, what organ in modern medicine is known to produce bile?",
        "answer": "liver"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What ancient Greek anatomist, who gave the modern sense to the term \"diagnosis,\" first propounded the fallacy that the liver was the source of the body's veins?",
        "answer": "Galen of Pergamon <DW> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A member of this family promised nuclear proliferation at the risk of his people \"having to eat grass.\" Operation Fair Play overthrew a member of this family who, with the Prime Minister of a larger eastern neighbor, signed the Simla Agreement. That leader was Zulfikar Ali. Following the assassination of a member of this family, Pervez Musharraf went into exile in 2007. For 10 points, give this last name of Benazir, an assassinated Prime Minister of Pakistan.",
        "answer": "Bhutto"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which surviving husband of Benazir Bhutto served as Pakistani President from 2008- 2013?",
        "answer": "Asif Ali Zardari <KG> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Resilient people during this time period used the slogan \"grab a root and growl\" and formed Last Man Clubs. This era led to the passage of the Frazier-Lemke Bankruptcy Act. The effects of this crisis are documented in Walker Evan's Let Us Now Praise Famous Men. This event worsened on Black Sunday, and it caused the migration of Okies. For 10 points, name this period in which storms and drought destroyed agriculture on the Great Plains.",
        "answer": "Dust Bowl"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Evans co-authored Let Us Now Praise Famous Men with which author of A Death in the Family?",
        "answer": "James Agee <JB> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Prior to 1800, New Jersey...",
      "prompt": "Name the prior to 1800, new jersey......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the third state, after only Delaware and Pennsylvania, to ratify what document?",
          "answer": "United States Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Moved its capital to what present-day capital city in 1790?",
          "answer": "Trenton, New Jersey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was entered by George Washington's crossing of what river on Christmas night, 1776?",
          "answer": "Delaware River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Delegates opposed what other state's plan to apportion legislative seats by population?",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the only state that allowed what group of people to vote from 1776 to 1807?",
          "answer": "women"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to what European colony around Fort Christina that was neither British nor Dutch?",
          "answer": "New Sweden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had as its first state governor what father-in-law of John Jay?",
          "answer": "William Livingston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Formed the southern part of what short-lived colonial union governed by Edmond Andros?",
          "answer": "Dominion of New England <DW> {II}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT IBERIA",
      "prompt": "In ancient times, the Iberian peninsula was home to…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "settlers from what Punic city in what's now Tunisia, home to the Barca family?",
          "answer": "Carthage"
        },
        {
          "question": "mines of what coinage metal mixed with gold to form electrum?",
          "answer": "silver"
        },
        {
          "question": "people who stereotypically had lots of what substance which Nazirites like Samson never cut?",
          "answer": "hair"
        },
        {
          "question": "what people of what's now Portugal who name a ship sunk in 1915?",
          "answer": "Lusitanii"
        },
        {
          "question": "speakers of what language group that includes Breton and Manx?",
          "answer": "Celtic languages"
        },
        {
          "question": "what emperor who ruled Rome at the empire's greatest territorial extent?",
          "answer": "Trajan"
        },
        {
          "question": "what rival of nearby Cádiz and ancient harbor city outside the Mediterranean?",
          "answer": "Tartessus"
        },
        {
          "question": "what type of sculpture exemplified by the ancient Lady of Elche and Lady of Baza?",
          "answer": "portrait busts <MJ> {II}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SHIPS AND BOATS",
      "prompt": "What type of ship or boat…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "can be fully submerged underwater, and attack with torpedoes?",
          "answer": "submarines"
        },
        {
          "question": "was used by vikings in their journeys across Northern Europe?",
          "answer": "longships"
        },
        {
          "question": "is created by the Inuit from whale remains?",
          "answer": "kayaks"
        },
        {
          "question": "was a battleship that started a naval arms race when first created by the Royal Navy in 1906?",
          "answer": "dreadnoughts"
        },
        {
          "question": "is a large Chinese flagship whose sails are supported by bamboo?",
          "answer": "junks"
        },
        {
          "question": "was a Roman design adding two rows of oars to the most iconic Ancient Greek warship?",
          "answer": "quinquiremes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a fast, small ship used by the Portuguese in exploration?",
          "answer": "caravels"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was an ancient Illyrian warship commonly used by pirates?",
          "answer": "lembus <JL> {II}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was booed roundly at a convention after Everett Dirksen said he took the party \"down the road to defeat.\" This man argued against outlawing the Communist Party, saying \"you can't shoot an idea with a gun\" in a debate with Harold (20 pts)",
        "Stassen. A Louisville newspaper joked that his speeches contained such clichés as \"Our future lies ahead.\" This candidate, who was often attacked as too close to the (10 pts)",
        "\"do-nothing Congress,\" was the New York District Attorney who convicted mobster Lucky Luciano. For 10 points, name this man who lost the 1948 presidential election to Harry Truman."
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Edmund Dewey"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s most prominent Interior Minister was Clifford Sifton. This man’s namesake “age” of rapid economic expansion and mass immigration included two new provinces added to confederation. This man succeeded Charles Tupper in his highest post, solved the (20 pts)",
        "Manitoba Schools Question, and authorized sending volunteers to South Africa for the Boer War. He said that “the twentieth (10 pts)",
        "century belongs to Canada.” This leader of the Liberals from 1887 to 1911 is depicted on the five-dollar bill. For 10 points, name this first French-Canadian Prime Minister."
      ],
      "answer": "Wilfrid Laurier <MW/PL> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this group personally strangled the imprisoned priest Philip II. Nicholas of Salos advocated against this group while pretending to be a \"holy fool.\" The German adventurer Heinrich von Staden provided an account of this group, which the (20 pts)",
        "Zemsky Sobor unsuccessfully tried to dissolve. Members of this group used the symbol of a dog's head, wore dark robes (10 pts)",
        ", and carried brooms. This group ruled a namesake land from a private court and perpetrated atrocities like the 1570 massacre in Novgorod. For 10 points, name this secret police service of Ivan the Terrible."
      ],
      "answer": "oprichniki <JB> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A “declaration” authored by senator John S. Carlile led to this action, which Waitman T. Willey proclaimed a “triple treason.” This action was ratified in an 1871 Supreme Court case concerning the Berkeley and Jefferson counties. “Kanawha” was a proposed name for the (20 pts)",
        "political entity created with this action. The Wheeling Convention called for this action in protest of the “Ordinance (10 pts)",
        "of Secession” that had been approved months earlier at Richmond. For 10 points, name this 1861 action in which a pro-Union state was created from part of the Confederate heartland."
      ],
      "answer": "splitting of West Virginia from Virginia <AG> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Decades before Pierre Bourdieu, this European spent years comparing the mountain- dwelling Kabyle people to nearby Arabs. This author of a Report on Algeria claimed that \"omnipotence\" easily accrued in the hands of an artistically-indifferent, dull-witted (20 pts)",
        "majority in his most famous book. This ethnic Norman assessed the historical failings of his own aristocratic social class in The Old Regime and the (10 pts)",
        "Revolution. He worked with Gustave de Beaumont on a book originally intended as study of prisons in the New World. For 10 points, name this French thinker who recalled his 1830s travels in Democracy in America."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexis Charles Henri Clerel de Tocqueville <AK/MJ> {III}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before this battle, Quintus Dellius switched sides, bringing battle plans with him. This battle’s losing commander burned many of his undermanned ships after a malaria outbreak swept through his army. The city of Nicopolis was founded after this battle, which took place at the (20 pts)",
        "mouth of the Ambracian Gulf. The victor at this battle adopted the title (10 pts)",
        "princeps and sent a military force led by Marcus Agrippa. For 10 points, name this naval battle in 31 BC, in which Mark Antony was defeated by Augustus’s forces."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Actium <KG> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country has expressed concerns over a neighboring country's Cattenom nuclear power plant. A fortress in this country was built on the Block promontory on land acquired by its first count, Siegfried. That fortress was once called the (20 pts)",
        "\"Gibraltar of the North\" and was dismantled following an 1867 crisis that involved France and (10 pts)",
        "Prussia. This country has Europe's highest GDP per capita, and is currently ruled by Henri, its Grand Duke. For 10 points, name this tiny country that borders France, Germany, and Belgium."
      ],
      "answer": "Grand Duchy of Luxembourg <KG> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following an event in this city, Evelyn Barker gave an order banning \"social intercourse\" with a certain group. Fortified areas called Bevingrads were constructed in this city, which was to be the center of an uprising planned by Revisionist leader Vladimir Jabotinsky. The (20 pts)",
        "Stern Gang assassinated Folke Bernadotte in this city. Explosives hidden in milk cans were used to (10 pts)",
        "blow up a hotel in this city by the Irgun. For 10 points, name this city, the capital of British Mandatory Palestine, which in 1948 became the capital of David Ben-Gurion's Israel."
      ],
      "answer": "Jerusalem <JB> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, a member of the SRs, Ivan Kalyayev, threw a bomb and assassinated Duke Sergius. A mutiny occurred on the Potemkin during this year, as did a strike that stopped activity on the (20 pts)",
        "Trans-Siberian Railway. On the January of this year, Father Gapon led a group of protesters who were fired upon at the Winter Palace. The (10 pts)",
        "October Manifesto was drawn up by Sergei Witte in this year. Earlier in this year, unrest was sparked following Bloody Sunday. For 10 points, name this year during which an uprising two revolutions prior to the Bolsheviks occurred against Nicholas II of Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "1905 <JL> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this battle, one of the women in the Biggerstaff household pleaded with the Isaac Shelby, a winning commander, to stop hanging prisoners. Despite the white flag raised by Abraham DePeyster, bloodthirsty soldiers on the winning side of this battle were eager to avenge the (20 pts)",
        "Waxhaw Massacre four months prior. At this battle, the Loyalist commander Patrick (10 pts)",
        "Ferguson was shot dead on his horse. For 10 points, name this 1780 victory for the Patriots during the Revolutionary War, fought along the border between South and North Carolina in an elevated area."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Kings Mountain <AG> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A coach of this college football team said he took the job because \"Mama called.\" After this school was torched in a game by black USC running back Sam Cunningham, a coach noted that game \"did more to integrate\" the state \"in 60 minutes\" than the whole life of Martin Luther King. Its longtime coach wore a trademark (20 pts)",
        "black and white houndstooth hat and presided over such talent as quarterback Joe (10 pts)",
        "Namath. For 10 points, name this college football team from the SEC which won six national titles under coach Bear Bryant, the arch-rival of Auburn."
      ],
      "answer": "University of Alabama <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's battles with Oakland County prosecutor Richard Thompson may have contributed to Thompson losing an election. Geoffrey Fieger represented this man in a series of trials that involved his use of a device called the \"Thanatron.\" While terminally ill with Hepatitis C, this man was (20 pts)",
        "paroled by Governor Jennifer Granholm in 2007. A videotape that aired on (10 pts)",
        "60 Minutes feared him daring the authorities to convict him for the killing of ALS sufferer Thomas Youk. For 10 points, name this physician who claimed to have helped over 100 people commit suicide."
      ],
      "answer": "Jacob “Jack” Kevorkian <MC> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 13"
    }
  ]
}